Jubril Joshua Juma

Email: jubril.juma@gmail.com | Portfolio Summary: jubriljuma.xyz

Background

While in university, I started volunteering for sales / business development roles with AIESEC to develop sales and leadership experience. During the 2013 school strike, I got a part - time role at a startup (4Forty Bus limited) which quickly evolved into a product manager role until it got acquired by Wakanow.com. I was offered a product manager role with the investing company, L5lab, with whom I worked part-time until I graduated from school in 2015. This to me, was like taking a second university major, because I learnt a lot from the team and was able to act upon my learnings within the 1 year+ that I was with L5lab. When I graduated from school I joined a football social network as a co - founder until it got acquired by iConcepts limited, and then founded another project (Verifi.ng) with 3 co - founders to solve the reliable person data problem in Nigeria. This is still an ongoing project, however, I stepped away from the day - to - day operations due to personal reasons. Currently, I help cross functional teams see the the world and "that" product through the eyes of the user to allow them build sustainable products. I am a very strong self-starter and a lover of data / data backed decision making.

Work Experience

April 2018 - Present

User Experience Researcher, Tusen Consulting at Google, Nigeria

- Currently working with the Google Go product team to provide Sub Saharan Africa user experience insights.
- Ran 7 lab studies in 1 country and 1 cohort survey in 4 countries.
- Built the Google Go user experience research website by using existing independent research

November 2016-August 2017

Founding Member / Head of Products & Operations, Verifi, Nigeria

- Grew the Pay product MAU from 0 -123 firms and processed NGN70m / USD194,000 in payroll in 6 months by using a combination of guerilla selling, iterative user research and AGILE product management.
- Led the product market fit of 1 revenue generating product Pay (payroll software), 1 parked product Assure (identity verification), and 1 pre launch product Inform (3rd party data pull API) using Lean AGILE product management coupled with user research.
- Scouted and recruited the 6 man team of developers from the founding team's personal networks.
- Setup our first 3 verification centres in the 3 business centres (Marina, Yaba, and Lekki) in Lagos by partnering with local businesses to host our centres

August 2015 – February 2017

Co - Founder / Products and Operations, Sangalo Limited, Nigeria

- Reduced OpEx by 65% in first 4 months by;
 - Recruiting a local operations team after transferring application development from Useful and Beautiful, South Africa
 - Using user research and iterative design to guide product strategy
 - Deployed a Lean-Agile Hybrid Framework, Continuous Integration & Project management tools.
- Cut the technical budget by 83% by;
 - o Recruiting and managing a team of local and remote developers,
 - o Designing and deploying stable, scalable software and server architecture,
 - Rebuilding the core of the product to attain stability, functionality and scalability,
 - Restructuring the project into Modules; Mobile App, Web App, Marketing & PR Platform, Data Warehouse.
 - o Tech Stack: Git, JIRA, Python, PHP, Mysql, MongoDB, BASH, Bamboo, Java
- Shipped the the first stable release product 12 weeks after of hiring a local team
- Acquired by iConcepts Limited in September 2016

Part - Time Experience

May 2014 – October 2015

Product Development Manager, L5lab Limited, Nigeria

- Oversaw the development and implementation of new software products (Kamdora.com, Betazoo, 440.ng, Salary.ng and Pass.ng) by working with the product team to execute marketing, product development and user experience plans.
- Introduced the Google iterative design approach by involving the product team in the Google UX Masterclass training. This led to the change in the culture of product development from opinionated to research and experience driven.
- Tech Stack: CodeIgniter PHP Framework, ASP.NET MVC (C#), MSSQL (CodeSmith), Git, JIRA, Bamboo, Confluence Microsoft Azure and Amazon Web Services

August 2013 - May 2014

Product Development Manager, 4Forty Bus Limited (an L5lab Investment), Nigeria

- Established the product development cycle using Trello and later, JIRA to manage feature requests until the acquisition of the company by www.Wakanow.com
- Led a successful Go-to-Market launch to acquire early adopters (MAU customer growth grew by 215%) by partnering
 with AIESEC Nigeria and the National Youth Service Corps to provide bus ticketing services for students and corps
 members during on peak periods.
- Managed and developed the life cycle of 3 products- BookingSync, Oya.com.ng and WebBooking

Other Activities

2017 UX and PM Mentor, <u>www.CodeMentor.com</u>, Remote

2015 iDEA GEM Mentor, iDEA Hub, Lagos, Nigeria

2014-Present Early stage startup investment and advisory; Alizarin Crimson Limited, and PRISE Limited, Shuttlers.ng,

BeatTraffik, Abee's Place, JAL Fund

2009 - 2015 Volunteer (multiple sales and marketing roles), AIESEC, Nigeria

Soft Skills Summary

Business Development | Investment Analysis | Productivity & Efficiency Improvements | Organisational Management & Planning | PMP and AGILE (SCRUM/Kanban/Lean/XP) | UX & UI Design | User Research and Testing | Web Site Analytics | Prototyping | Wireframing | Information Architecture (IA) | Requirements Definition | Software Development (HTML, CSS3, JavaScript/jQuery, PHP, Bootstrap 2 and 3, Wordpress) | Visual Design | Applications Development | Private Equity

Education

Formal

2009 - 2015 B. Sc., Genetics and Biotechnology, University of Calabar, Calabar, Nigeria

Short Courses

2017 Introduction to Hyperledger and other Distributed Ledger Technologies (Linux Foundation)

2016 Investment Management (University of Geneva, Switzerland)

2015 HTML 5

CSS3

2014

Firm and Corporate Business Strategy (Darden Business School, Virginia)

Lean Start-up Methodology

User Experience and Interactive Design

AGILE Methodologies (SCRUM/Kanban/Lean/XP)

Python

Project Management Introductory Finance

New Venture/Enterprise Development

2013 Google Analytics Professional Certified

2013 Associate Degree, Information Risk Management, University of Washington,

Washington DC, USA